A Guide to the Papers of Benjamin Griffith Brawley, 1928-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 3, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:41)
  Brawley sends Dillard news clippings [not present] from the Raleigh News and Observer about the winners of the "Live-at-Home Week" competition, "a white boy and a Negro girl." Brawley has not received final word about the publication date of the book. He has been given "special charge" of selling the first 1,000 copies. He asks if Dillard has a list of the Jeanes teachers with their addresses.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 5, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:42)
  Brawley has heard from Revell and the book "ought to be out about three weeks hence."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 10, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:43)
  Brawley received Dillard's two letters. He will "attend to the three points mentioned: the fifty personal copies, the brief ad in the newspapers, and the circular." Brawley will also send a copy of the book to "Mr. Rosenwald" [Julius Rosenwald] in hopes that he will order 5,000 copies, "a copy to be sent to each of his schools."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 14, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:44)
  Brawley received Dillard's letters and forwards proofs of the illustrations [not present]. Brawley is attending to the circular and asks if Dillard wants 4,000 copies rather than 3,000. He asks Dillard how he might "get the book included among those on the Rosenwald list?" Brawley also mentions that his book, A Social History of the American Negro, is out of print and is on the Rosenwald list. He ask Dillard for advice on getting the book reprinted.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 14, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:45)
  Brawley says that he was "so busy talking about the book" that he forgot to mention the situation at Shaw in his first letter of this date. "Dr. Smith of the Home Mission Society" was in Raleigh a month ago to review the situation and spoke at some length with Brawley. Brawley says there is to be a special trustees meeting in New York "on Thursday of this week." He hopes something will be done "for the college is suffering." One of the major issues is the "field secretary, appointed two years ago at the request of the alumni." There is a deficit of $4000 for the secretary's salary, which was supposed to be made up by July 1.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 23, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:46)
  Brawley hopes that "Mr. R. [Rosenwald?] will not feel at all as you think about the picture." He says the book has been printed, but not yet bound. "The situation at Shaw is far from good" but Brawley is hopeful about it. The trustees accepted the resignation of the president and will allow the field secretary to remain, but the alumni will be responsible for his salary. A committee has been appointed to hire a new president "and it has corrected a recent report by making it clear that it is perfectly free in its choice as between a white man and a Negro."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 16, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:47)
  Brawley tells Dillard the book "will be ready within a few days." The September issue of The Southern Workman will publish the chapter "Citizen of the World."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 18, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:48)
  Brawley hopes Dillard will like the finished book and apologizes for "mention of the phrase that I do not like on the inside of the flap of the jacket." Brawley is trying to have the jacket reprinted.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 19., ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:49)
  The first copies of the book have arrived and Brawley is sending a copy to Dillard.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 20, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:50)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letters and encloses two letters from Revell [not present]. Brawley will try to have the phrase "household word" changed on the jacket.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 22, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:51)
  Brawley is glad that Dillard is pleased with the book. He forwards a letter from Revell [not present] that informs him the phrase "household word" will be changed.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 August 23, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:52)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the "list of forty names and check for $75." He asks if "Miss Skinner of St. Louis and Professor Woodward and Mr. Kearny of New Orleans are being included on any list?"
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 September 1, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:53)
  Revell sent Brawley 100 copies as soon as the book was published; thus, Brawley is able "to fill without delay any orders that may come to me." He is sending 10 copies of the book and 4,500 copies of the circular to Dillard.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 September 8, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:54)
  Brawley has just received word from the Post Office in New York that several letters and the circulars were held for insufficient postage. Brawley thanks Dillard for taking care of the circular and tells him he is will be in Danville, Va. until Friday.
- Leo M. Favrot, Baton Rouge, La. to Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C., 1930 September 8, TL, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:55)
  Favrot praises the book and says Brawley is to be "congratulated not only for your keen insight into the life of a great man, but also for your pleasing, straightforward style, and for the orderly sequence of your narrative. More than that, I want particularly to express appreciation of your presentation of the viewpoint of a Southerner."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 September 12, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:56)
  Brawley has just returned from Danville where he had an operation on his throat. He mentions the postage situation in New York. Brawley says "President J.L. Peacock is thoroughly in charge" at Shaw this winter and is "counting on the Slater appropriation." Brawley mentions that he gave Revell a list of newspapers to receive press copies of the book. He encloses two letters [not present] praising the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 September 27, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:57)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the letters praising the book he sent and says "my wife suggests that I must not read many such things, as there is danger that my hatband will become a little tight." He mentions the possibility of another printing and discusses some possible corrections.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 October 1, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:58)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the letters and was sorry he missed seeing him on Monday. He mentions that he has received nice letters from "Dr. Shepardson" and "Dr. Dabney."
- Trevor Arnett, New York, to Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C., 1930 October 9, TL, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:59)
  Arnett thanks Brawley for a copy of the book and congratulates him.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 October 13, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:60)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for arranging "the conference in Washington." He sends a copy of a letter from Trevor Arnett [see 1930 October 9, above]. Brawley discusses additional charges from Revell for the production of the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 October 15, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:61)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter and says he will send a copy of the book to Miss Henrietta Ray. He asks Dillard to have the General Education Board send copies to The Virginia Quarterly Review and T he South Atlantic Quarterly.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 October 17, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:62)
  Brawley has read the letters Dillard sent and is forwarding a letter [not present] from "President Cuninggim of Scarritt College for Christian Workers in Nashville."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 October 24, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:63)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter of October 20 and says it is "certainly very kind of Dr. Stokes and Dr. Jones to be interested in the special matter of which we spoke." He says that Arthur D. Wright has been at Shaw for the last two days.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 December 2, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:64)
  Brawley hopes that Dillard "returned from Jamaica greatly refreshed. He returns the originals of the pictures used the in book [not present]."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 December 4, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:65)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the report on his trip to Jamaica; it interested Mrs. Brawley very much since she was born there. Brawley has sent a copy of the book to Mr. Embree in hopes of interesting Mr. Rosenwald in it. Brawley mentions that "Dr. Smith of the Home Mission Society" was at Shaw recently. Brawley thanks Dillard for his support and says he is not interested in taking "charge of the college." He says he "can see no hope unless Shaw can have at once an unusually progressive administration and secure at least $600,000 for new buildings." Should the Guggenheim fellowship come through, Brawley would hope to go on to a different position at its conclusion.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 December 16, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:66)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter. He says that "Shaw was stunned last night by the passing of Dean Turner."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 December 23, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:67)
  Brawley mentions a visit from George Foster Peabody. Brawley has only 21 copies remaining of the 100 he initially received from Revell; he can fill the order for "Mr. Tanner" but future orders should be sent to Revell. He closes by saying "Shaw is in turmoil again" but the story is long and "will keep till another day."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 January 8, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:68)
  Brawley discusses payment arrangements for the 97 copies of the book that Dillard ordered. Brawley says that things "at Shaw steadily get worse instead of better. Dr. Johnson at Howard has very kindly renewed his offer" and Brawley is "disposed to consider the matter favorably." A note in Dillard's hand says "would advise strongly to accept."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 January 29, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:69)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the news clippings he sent. Brawley reports that the students at Shaw protested the "appointment of Dr. Redfern as dean" and Brawley was asked "to take up the extra work." On February 14, Brawley will be talking to President Johnson [at Howard University] "more definitely." He says that his "relation to this institution of course is such as to lead to some embarrassment if I leave; but at present I can see nothing else to do. Can you?"
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 February 2, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:70)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for sending "notices" about the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 May 28, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:71)
  Brawley expects "to be in Washington" by next Thursday and gives Dillard his new address. He says that the first printing of the book is almost exhausted.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 July 10, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:72)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for "the communications with reference to the advance of the Jeanes work in South America." He comments on Dillard's retirement and encloses clippings [not present] from The Age and The Afro-American. Brawley says that a second printing of the book appears likely. He mentions "the problem of housing" in Washington and says he hopes to "move from our temporary quarters" by September.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 July 16, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:73)
  Brawley says that Revell will print an addition 500 copies for an advance of $325. Brawley is unable to advance the money; he has asked "Mr. Roy" if the Phelps Stokes Fund would be able to do so but has not had a reply. He asks Dillard if "through the Jeanes Fund or otherwise that you will be able to help to move a considerable portion of 500 copies within the next three or four months?" He closes by saying that he and Mrs. Brawley "are very glad that we heeded your advice to leave Raleigh immediately."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1931 July 20, ALS, 4 p. (Box-folder 1:74)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter. The new printing of the book will go forward and Brawley is "assuming financial responsibility." He is not allowing the type to be dispersed in case another printing is needed. Brawley will have most of the copies of the new printing and will fill orders for more than a single copy. Brawley says that if the "book is worth anything in race relations" it would be "most effective if put to work in some of the smaller cities and towns throughout the South." He would like to have copies sent "to at least a few hundred small town principals, both white and colored, but mainly white. Many of these men do not buy many new books and they would talk about something like this much more than a college president."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1932 September 10, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:74a)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for sending a copy of his article, "Teachers and Reading" and says it reminds him "more and more why I have been attracted to your work." Dillard's interest is in all children and Brawley says "[s]o is mine." He says that he has "always been thrilled by what was being done by Miss Martha Berry and others for the white boys and girls in the mountains." Brawley says that five or six years ago he "conceived the idea that my final work as a teacher was to cultivate better reading habits on the part of Negro boys and girls throughout the South." He presented the idea to the General Education Board. He hoped to "see as closely as possible just what books were available for reading in hundreds of schools throughout the South. Then I wanted to select and supply ten or twenty books as the individual case might require." He believed a foundation, on the order of the Jeanes Fund, would be required to effect his plan, but he received little encouragement. "It is far easier to get a hundred thousand for a building than for anything that goes more directly into character building."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1934 January 29, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:75)
  Brawley was happy to receive Dillard's letter as he had heard Dillard was "troubled by illness." Brawley now has all remaining copies of the book but he is "not rushing about getting rid of these at any cheap rate." He thanks Dillard for the circular he sent [not present] and says he shares "your enthusiasm for 'David Grayson'" [Ray Stannard Baker]. Brawley spoke "last night" for the annual Hampton Founder's Day meeting. He says it went well except the quartet "sang too many mournful spirituals."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1934 September 27, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:76)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his order for four copies of the book and says there are now less than sixty remaining.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1934 December 19, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:77)
  Brawley has heard that Dillard has been sick and hopes he is "a great deal better." He understands that Dillard is "heading the Scottsboro Committee" and can "hardly imagine a more patriotic service." Brawley's new book, Early Negro American Writers, is to be published by the University of North Carolina Press in about two months.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1935 January 2, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:78)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for sending the letter "from my old college dean, Dr. Shepardson" [not present]. He hopes Dillard's health has improved and mentions having attended the "Modern Language meeting."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1935 March 15, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:79)
  Brawley is glad to hear Dillard's health has improved and thanks him for sending "the reprinted articles" [not present]. Brawley also thanks Dillard for the inscribed copy of Dillard's book, From News Stand to Cyrano. Brawley says "a few designing men have recently launched a new attack on the administration at Howard, but I am happy to tell you that the tide is now strongly in President Johnson's favor." Brawley and several other Howard faculty members recently attended a special dinner at the Willard Hotel. The Secretary of the Interior was present and Brawley has since sent him a copy of Doctor Dillard of the Jeanes Fund.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1936 January 21, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:80)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter and enclosure [not present]. He hopes Dillard's health is improving.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1936 March 3, TLS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:81)
  Brawley thanks Dillard again for the inscribed copy of From News Stand to Cyrano and says that if Dillard has extra copies of any of his earlier works, Brawley would appreciate receiving them. Brawley say that he is "trying to get together as many things as I can in the field of Negro literature. The emphasis is not so much on history or the so-called problem, but literature." He says he has most of James Weldon Johnson's books and many by younger writers but the earlier generation's books are much hard to come by. "Just think of the fact that the little book, Oak and Ivy, that young Dunbar used to beg people on his elevator to buy, is now worth ten or twelve dollars and can hardly be had for either love or money." Brawley mentions that he has most of Dunbar's works, as well as a copy of the 1773 edition of Phillis Wheatley's Poems on Various Subjects. He mentions other authors including Charles Chesnutt, W.E.B. Du Bois, Alexander Crummell, William Wells Brown, Frederick Douglass, Booker T. Washington, Joel Chandler Harris, Walter Hines Page and William Garrott Brown. Brawley says that "in the wider field of literature" he has "what must be (if I can believe the dealers) the best Le Gallienne collection in this part of the world." Brawley concludes with a discussion of "the biographical series that I have under way with the University of North Carolina Press."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to James Hardy Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1938 June 7, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:82)
  Having "just graded the last examination papers and made out my report" Brawley finds himself "thinking about the meaning of it all." He said he has especially thought of Dillard and his "paper about the early days in Norfolk, 'A School of the Past.'" Brawley hopes Dillard is well.
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1938 July 6, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:83)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the check and his interest in Brawley's publications. He says that at least two of his book are out of print "so that I shall doubtless have to send not just one or two but several books other than my own to make up the difference." He says "it may be that I can help Miss Carothers with a few items I have recently seen here in second hand stores." Brawley recently attended "a meeting of the Executive Committee of the Encyclopedia... and there were several kind references to you." A postscript in Brawley's hand says that the Committee "voted to invite Professor Guy B. Johnson to be co-editor with Dr. Du Bois."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1938 July 8, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:84)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the additional check and says he will report in about two weeks. He will communicate with Miss Carothers "to see about some items that she may or may not have."
- Benjamin Brawley, Washington, D.C. to J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1938 July 14, TLS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:85)
  Brawley has "to-day sent to Miss Carothers at Dillard University two packages containing the books listed on separate sheet" [p.2]. Brawley says this "has reminded me of two dreams I had but that are still unrealized. One was to preside over a fund of about half a million for the purchase of books for needy schools and communities. The other was to have for Negro boys an academy, a secondary school with the highest standards of scholarship and character."